A Guide to the Papers of Beverly Randolph Middleton 1945-1974
Special Collections and University Archives, Patricia W. and J. Douglas Perry Library
Special Collections and University Archives, Patricia W. and J. Douglas Perry Library, Old Dominion University
Papers of Beverly Randolph Middleton 1945-1974
Special Collections and University Archives, Patricia W. and J. Douglas Perry Library, Old Dominion University
MG 64
3 Document Cases and 1 Oversize Box; 3 linear feet
Administrative Information
Access
Open to researchers without restrictions.
Acquisition Information
A gift of Ernestine K. Middleton, December 1998.
Biographical/Historical Information
Beverly Randolph Middleton was born on September 7, 1928, in Norfolk County, Virginia. He graduated from Norview High School where he was a gifted athlete and a central force in both Norview's football and basketball varsity programs. After high school he began his university career at the Virginia Polytechnic Institute where again his athletic abilities stood out as a member and co-captain of the track and field team. Middleton finished his University career at VPI graduating with a Bachelor of Science degree in Electrical Engineering.
At VPI Middleton was enrolled in the Army cadet program. After college he joined the U.S. Army, and served from 1951 to 1953, attaining the rank of Captain. He was stationed in Europe where he received a special commendation from Queen Julianne of the Netherlands for his devoted and persevering personal assistance in coming to aid in a time of national crisis.
In 1967 Middleton was elected to the Virginia House of Delegates representing the city of Virginia Beach on a Democratic Union party ticket that opposed the Kellam Machine. He was a member of the House of Delegates from 1968 until 1974, having been defeated in his bid for re-election in 1973. He served three consecutive terms. The five committees on which he served were: Appropriations, Education, Roads, Chesapeake Bay and its Tributaries, and Conservation and Natural Resources. From 1972 to 1982 he was a member, appointed by the Governor of Virginia, of both the Virginia Housing Study Commission and the State Board of Housing and Development. Middleton also served as a member of the Chesapeake Bay Bridge-Tunnel Commission and on the General Advisory Council for Vocational Education for Virginia Beach schools.
Beverly R. Middleton was a licensed professional engineer and retired as president of Middleton Construction Company. He was a member of several organizations including the Society of Professional Engineers and the Builders and Contractors Exchange. He served as director of the latter organization. He chaired the Joint Apprenticeship Committee of the Tidewater Electrical Industry from 1961 to 1974. He also served as president of the Suburban Kiwanis Club and Thoroughgood Civic League and was a member of the Royal Order of the Neptune Festival and Bayside Presbyterian Church.
Middleton died on July 12, 1996, was married twice and is survived by his second wife, Ernestine W. Middleton. He fathered three sons and four daughters: John Middleton, Barry Knight, Wayne Middleton, Shannon Knight, Gale Dunlap, Beverly Middleton Hathaway, and Terry Burton. He was active in coaching little league football and basketball and enjoyed bird hunting and fishing.
Scope and Content Information
The papers of Beverly R. Middleton deal primarily with his athletic career at Virginia Polytechnic Institute from 1945 until 1949 and his political career from 1967 to 1974. The collection provides an adequate look at Beverly R. Middleton's athletic career at VPI.
The political aspects of the collection which concentrate heavily on his election and re-election campaigns in 1967, 1969, and 1971 as well as political correspondence from 1970 until mid-1971 provide a genuine examination of his political aspirations. Included in this collection is some sparse material that gives hints to both his athletic career at Norview High School and his career after he left the Virginia House of Delegates. The collection provides a perspective look into the growth of Middleton's public image from a star athlete to a Virginia Beach delegate.
The documents and materials in the Beverly R. Middleton collection are divided into eight series entitled in order of appearance: correspondence, campaign files, organizations, printed material, photographs, artifacts, newspaper clippings, and scrapbooks.
Organization
The documents and materials in the Beverly R. Middleton collection are divided into eight series entitled in order of appearance: correspondence, campaign files, organizations, printed material, photographs, artifacts, newspaper clippings, and scrapbooks.
Series I - Correspondence
The majority of materials in this series consists mostly of political correspondence written between 1970 and 1971. The folder inventory of this series is separated into three sub-series. Correspondence from 1970 and 1971 is divided into two sub-series separated by year while the third sub-series consists of invitations and thank you letters. The political correspondence is divided by topic and consists mostly of letters from concerned citizens with replies from Delegate Middleton concerning specific legislation. Personal correspondence as well as invitations to several inaugurations for the governors of Virginia from 1978 to 1990 constitutes the last sub-series in this series.
Among the correspondence are letters composed by citizens concerning the Save Old Dominion University campaign of 1970, letters from Congressman G. William Whitehurst regarding Boater Safety, personal invitations and correspondence with Governor John B. Dalton, and a personal thank you letter and autographed photo from Congressman Thomas N. Downing. Also, there is a Table of Contents outlining correspondence from 1971.
Series II - Campaign Files
The material in this series includes packet guides for campaign volunteers and poll workers, campaign stationery, press releases and speeches made by Middleton during his election and re-election campaigns, and a poll book registration of voters who voted on September 14, 1971. Items of note are handwritten notes and documents pertaining to the 1971 Middleton Campaign Fund which include a list of contributors in 1971 and a compilation of registered voters by counties/cities as of January 1, 1970.
Series III - Organizations
The papers in this series include correspondence from the Virginia Beach Women's Democratic Club and a flyer from the Thoroughgood Garden Club. Papers of interest include correspondence, newspaper clippings, and other documents pertaining to the Virginia Building Officials Conference.
Series IV - Printed Material
This series consists of a printed newsletter and an official program for a sporting event sponsored by Kiwanis International. Middleton was a member and also served as president of the Suburban Kiwanis Club. The Virginia Housing Development Authority - 1982 Annual Report also appears in this series. The most prominent item of special interest however is an official program from the testimonial dinner honoring Senator Harry F. Byrd, Jr., with the establishment of an endowment fund in his name at the Virginia Military Institute.
Series V - Photographs
The photographs in this series include: a photo of the Norview High School football team, Middleton in track and field attire and cadet uniforms, and Middleton presiding over a Kiwanis Club conference. Of note are photographs of Governor Linwood Holton with State Senator James Turk, presiding over a press conference after the Virginia Housing Study Commissions Final Report on the housing crisis.
Series VI - Artifacts
This series contains Virginia Delegate license plates, a cocktail napkin from the Middleton campaign, and a bumper sticker from a Middleton re-election campaign.
Series VII - Newspaper Clippings
The newspaper articles in this series concern both Middleton's election and re-election campaigns and his family. There are several miscellaneous newspaper clippings, which concern Middleton's family from 1938 to 1941.
Series VIII - Scrapbooks
The four scrapbooks in this series are relatively intact; however, there are certain items which have been displaced and are now located in folders of their own. The four scrapbooks in this series each relate to a specific time frame. Scrapbook I is a compilation of items related to either Middleton's athletic career at VPI or his career as a Cadet in Company "B" from 1945 to 1949. The scrapbook also mentions his high school athletic career. The other three scrapbooks incorporate Middleton's political career including his election and re-election campaigns for the Virginia House of Delegates. Each scrapbook focuses on one particular campaign: 1967 United Campaign and Democratic primary, 1969 re-election campaign, and 1971 re-election campaign. In the scrapbooks concerning Middleton's re-election campaigns of 1969 and 1971 there are several items which relate to his tenure in the Virginia House of Delegates in that particular time frame.
Contents List
- Correspondence
  - 1970
    - Abortion Laws I Dec. 18, 1969 - Jan. 30, 1970 (Box-folder 1:1)
    - Abortion Laws II Feb. 1-4, 1970 (Box-folder 1:2)
    - Abortion Laws III Feb. 6-23, 1970 (Box-folder 1:3)
    - Blue Laws Feb. 17-25, 1970 (Box-folder 1:4)
    - Conservation and Pollution Jan. 25 - Feb. 13, 1970 (Box-folder 1:5)
    - Cigarette Tax Mar. 1-11, 1970 (Box-folder 1:6)
    - Drug Control Jan. 14 - Feb. 28, 1970 (Box-folder 1:7)
    - Education I Jan. 22 - Feb. 20, 1970 (Box-folder 1:8)
    - Education II Feb. 21 - Mar. 11, 1970 (Box-folder 1:9)
    - Gas Tax Bill Feb. 2 - Mar. 5, 1970 (Box-folder 1:10)
    - Hospital Legislation Dec. 31, 1969 - Mar. 1, 1970 (Box-folder 1:11)
    - Interest Rates Jan. 10 - Mar. 5, 1970 (Box-folder 1:12)
    - Library Support Jan. 19, 1970 (Box-folder 1:13)
    - Licensing of Electronic Technicians Dec. 22, 1969 (Box-folder 1:14)
    - Personal Jan. 12 - Feb. 4, 1970 (Box-folder 1:15)
    - Pest Control Legislation Dec. 23-24, 1969 (Box-folder 1:16)
    - Port Facilities Jan. 23 - Feb. 23, 1970 (Box-folder 1:17)
    - Save Old Dominion University I Jan. 29 - Feb. 24, 1970 (Box-folder 1:18)
    - Save Old Dominion University II February 16 - 20, 1970 (Box-folder 1:19)
    - Save Old Dominion University III Feb. 22 - Mar. 4, 1970 (Box-folder 1:20)
    - Science Museum Complex Nov. 6, 1969 - Jan. 13, 1970 (Box-folder 1:21)
    - State Aid to Private Schools Jan. 26 - Feb. 12, 1970 (Box-folder 1:22)
    - Special Education I Jan. 17 - Feb. 14, 1970 (Box-folder 1:23)
    - Special Education II Feb. 16 - Mar. 6, 1970 (Box-folder 1:24)
    - Twin Trailers and Trucking I Jan. 27 - Feb. 9, 1970 (Box-folder 1:25)
    - Twin Trailers and Trucking II Feb. 9 - 20, 1970 (Box-folder 1:26)
    - United Parcel Service, includes article "A Bill" Jan. 19, 1970 (Box-folder 1:27)
    - Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University Dec. 3, 1969 - Feb. 5, 1970 (Box-folder 1:28)
    - Miscellaneous I Jan. 1970 (Box-folder 1:29)
    - Miscellaneous II Feb. 2-10, 1970 (Box-folder 2:1)
    - Miscellaneous III Feb. 11-18, 1970 (Box-folder 2:2)
    - Miscellaneous IV Feb. 20 - 25, 1970 (Box-folder 2:3)
    - Miscellaneous V Mar. 1970 (Box-folder 2:4)
  - 1970
    - Table of Contents, Files 1971 (Box-folder 2:5)
    - Appalachian Trail Jan. 6 - Feb. 7, 1971 (Box-folder 2:6)
    - Boater Safety (includes correspondence with the Honorable G. William Whitehurst) Jan. 15 - 18, 1971 (Box-folder 2:7)
    - Conflict of Interest Feb. 11, 1971 (Box-folder 2:8)
    - Congratulations (to the Tidewater Scholastic Team) Jan. 21, 1971 (Box-folder 2:9)
    - Congratulatory Letters (for victory in the Democratic Primary) Sept. 15, 1971 (Box-folder 2:10)
    - Personal Correspondence Jan. 12 - 27, 1971 (Box-folder 2:11)
    - Recommendations Feb. 9, 1971 (Box-folder 2:12)
    - School Children, Correspondence from Feb. 1, 1971 (Box-folder 2:13)
    - School Visiting Jan. 28, 1971 (Box-folder 2:14)
    - Sewerage (includes newspaper article) Jan. 6, 1971 (Box-folder 2:15)
    - State Corporate Commission Jan. 18, 1971 (Box-folder 2:16)
    - State Owned Land Jan. 18 - Feb. 16, 1971 (Box-folder 2:17)
    - Taxes (School, Church, Hospital) jan. 6-26, 1971 (Box-folder 2:18)
    - Land Use Tax Jan. 27, 1971 (Box-folder 2:19)
    - Virginia Beach Zoning Ordinance Jan. 29 - Feb. 18, 1971 (Box-folder 2:20)
    - 2:21 Jan. 22, 1971 (Box-folder 2:21)
  - Invitations and Thank You Letters
    - Invitation I (to the Inauguration of the Governor of Virginia) 1978 and 1982 (Box-folder 2:22)
    - Invitation II (to the Inauguration of the Governor of Virginia) 1986 and 1990 (Box-folder 2:23)
    - Invitation III (Christmas card and letter from Governor John B. Dalton) 1977 (Box-folder 2:24)
    - Invitation IV (to the Republican Senatorial Circle Spring Briefing and Spring Gala Dinner Dance) 1990 (Box-folder 2:25)
    - Thank You letter from Thomas N. Downing (includes picture) Nov. 7, 1968 (Box-folder 2:26)
- Campaign Files
  - Campaign Stationary: "Vote for Lowell K. Clark for the House" and "Elect Holloman House of Delegates" undated (Box-folder 2:27)
  - Election Campaign Brochures for the House of Delegates undated (Box-folder 2:28)
  - Genealogical Chart of Middleton Family undated (Box-folder 2:29)
  - Guidelines and Procedures for Candidates including compilation of registered voters by counties and cities as of Jan. 1, 1970 Mar. 12, 1971 (Box-folder 2:30)
  - Handwritten Notes Concerning Campaign Supporters and Helpers 1971 (Box-folder 2:31)
  - Middleton Campaign Fund (includes list of Contributors) 1971 (Box-folder 2:32)
  - Packet for Precinct Captains (includes tips, schedules for poll workers, petition for qualified voters in primary elections, and registered voters by precinct in Virginia Beach) 1971 (Box-folder 2:33)
  - Press Releases and Speeches 1971 (Box-folder 2:34)
  - Tips for a Candidate's Wife undated (Box-folder 2:35)
  - Tips for Poll Workers undated (Box-folder 2:36)
  - Virginia Beach Map for Voting Precincts 1969 (Box-folder 2:37)
  - Voter Registration and Sign-In Sept. 14, 1971 (Box-folder 2:38)
- Organizations
  - Thoroughgood Garden Club (flyer) Dec. 1-2, 1984 (Box-folder 2:39)
  - Virginia Beach Women's Democratic Club undated (Box-folder 2:40)
  - Virginia Building Officials' Conference undated (Box-folder 2:41)
- Printed Materials
  - Kiwanis International - Kiwanis Bowl Program Sept. 4, 1965 (Box-folder 3:1)
  - Kiwanis News Letters Dec. 16, 1975 and Feb. 22, 1977 (Box-folder 3:2)
  - A Salute to Senator Harry F. Byrd, Jr. Dec. 6, 1982 (Box-folder 3:3)
  - Virginia Housing Development Authority Annual Report 1982 (Box-folder 3:4)
- Photographs
  - Norview High School Football Team undated (Box-folder 3:5)
  - VPI Track undated (Box-folder 3:6)
  - Cadet Company "B" at VPI undated (Box-folder 3:7)
  - Governor Holton receives Housing Study Report Jan. 27, 1971 (Box-folder 3:8)
  - Press Conference after Virginia Housing Study Commissions final report Nov. 15, 1971 (Box-folder 3:9)
  - Middleton presiding over Kiwanis International meeting undated (Box-folder 3:10)
  - Middleton and unknown persons undated (Box-folder 3:11)
- Artifacts
  - Bumper Sticker: "Guy and Middleton House of Delegates" undated (Box-folder 3:12)
  - Cocktail Napkin with Seal undated (Box-folder 3:13)
  - Virginia Delegate License Plate I 1972 (Box-folder 3:14)
  - Virginia Delegate License Plate II 1974 (Box-folder 3:15)
- Newspaper Clippings
  - Miscellaneous Newspaper Clippings (from The Norfolk Ledger-Dispatch) 1938-1939 (Box-folder 3:16)
  - Miscellaneous Newspaper Clippings (from the Norfolk Ledger-Dispatch) 1940-1941 (Box-folder 3:17)
  - Newspaper article concerning John and Wayne Middleton: "Spring Brings Outdoor Games," The Beacon April 12, 1963 (Box-folder 3:18)
  - Newspaper Campaign Advertisements c. 1971 (Box-folder 3:19)
  - Newspaper article concerning Mrs. B.R. Middletone: "Candidate's Wife Important Too," The Beacon Oct. 14, 1971 (Box-folder 3:20)
- Scrapbooks
  - Annual Banquet German Club at VPI (from scrapbook I) May 26, 1948 (Box-folder 3:21)
  - Athletic Awards for track at VPI (from scrapbook I) undated (Box-folder 3:22)
  - Baccalaureate Sermon at Norview High School (from scrapbook I) 1945 (Box-folder 3:23)
  - Button and Ribbon from United Campaign (from scrapbook II) 1967 (Box-folder 3:24)
  - Cadet Corps Mid-Winter Formal (from scrapbook I) Feb. 7, 1948 (Box-folder 3:25)
  - Letter of Congratulations from young Stephanne Caverly (from scrapbook III) undated (Box-folder 3:26)
  - Newspaper Advertisement for United Campaign (from scrapbook II) 1967 (Box-folder 3:27)
  - Newspaper articles on United Campaign (from scrapbook II - includes Article from The New York Times dated July 12, 1967) 1967 (Box-folder 3:28)
  - Newspaper articles from The Daily-News Record (Harrisonburg, VA) about Virginia's High School Basketball Championship (from scrapbook I) Mar. 9-10, 1945 (Box-folder 3:29)
  - Newspaper articles concerning B.R. Middleton's VPI track career 1945-1949 from The Virginia Tech (University Newsletter) and The Richmond News Leader (from Scrapbook I) 1945-1949 (Box-folder 3:30)
  - Newspaper articles from The Ledger Star (from scrapbook III) 1970 (Box-folder 3:31)
  - Newspaper articles from The Virginian-Pilot and The Richmond News Leader (from scrapbook III) 1973 (Box-folder 3:32)
  - Newspaper articles, miscellaneous (from scrapbook III) undated (Box-folder 3:33)
  - Number worn at unknown track meet includes signature (from scrapbook I) undated (Box-folder 3:34)
  - Official Program, Southern Conference Track Meet (from scrapbook I) May 14-15, 1948 (Box-folder 3:35)
  - Official Program, University of Maryland Indoor Track Meet (from scrapbook I) Feb. 21, 1948 (Box-folder 3:36)
  - Official Program for Virginia's High School Basketball Championship (from scrapbook I) Mar. 9, 1945 (Box-folder 3:37)
  - Postcard addresssed to Mrs. Middleton (mother of B.R.) from North Carolina (from Scrapbook I) undated (Box-folder 3:38)
  - "Tech Sports Revue's" from The Virginia Tech (from scrapbook I) undated (Box-folder 3:39)
  - Telegram from Richard D. Guy concerning vote against State Corporation Commission Control (from scrapbook III) June 11, 1969 (Box-folder 3:40)
  - United Contributions Report (from Scrapbook II) 1967 (Box-folder 3:41)
  - Athletic Career at VPI (also small exerpts of Norview High School athletic career) 1945-1949 (Box-folder 4:1)
  - United Campaign, July Democratic Party 1967, Middleton for House of Delegates (Box-folder 4:2)
  - Re-election campaign 1969 (Box-folder 4:3)
  - Re-election campaign 1971 (Box-folder 4:4)